A Guide to the Additional Papers of Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1874-1953
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - William Baker Powell "Billy" to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1939-1947 (Box-folder 28:2)
    Powell wrote to Ada asking for information on the best hotels and restaurants in Charlottesville, Virginia for an article that he was writing. He was also asked by the Olympic Games Press Committee to write for them in Helsinki in 1940. He mentioned the "terrible news" on the radio about war starting out in Europe. In February 1941 Ada's husband, Professor Thomas Beardsworth died. Powell travelled to Ireland, England, and the Riviera. He mentioned VE day and the Médaile Militarie given to Winston Churchill. He wrote to Ada that Europe "is not normal yet" and that there was a railroad strike in France.
  - William Baker Powell "Billy" to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1948-1953; n.d, 22 items. (Box-folder 28:3)
    Powell wrote that he was commissioned by House Beautiful to do a series of articles on what to buy in Copenhagen, Brussels and Paris. He mentioned attending Cole's new show, Kiss Me, Kate. He travelled to London and mentioned that London was very gay for Queen Elizabeth's coronation. There is also a napkin that was made by a Russian noble woman in one of his letters.
  - Pictures Powell to Ada, n. d., 10 items. (Box-folder 28:4)
  - Warren Rice to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1891, 4 items. (Box-folder 28:5)
    Warren Rice, a school friend of Ada's wrote to her from Winchester while she was in Frederick, Maryland. He mentioned Will Glass getting into trouble at school and that he did not like their teacher [Lillian].
  - Albert Romero, 1891-1894, 22 items. (Box-folder 28:6)
    Romero was a friend of Will Glass and attended the University of Virginia. He was a member of Zeta Psi.
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1903-1905, 17 items. (Box-folder 28:7)
    Blanche was worried she was "in trouble" [pregnant?] and didn't want to have another child. She mentioned using carbolic acid for an abortion.
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1906-1917, 24 items. (Box-folder 28:8)
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1918-1921, 17 items. (Box-folder 28:9)
    Blanche mentioned the inauguration of President Warren G. Harding. She also wrote about being nostalgic for the "good old days of slavery."
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1922-1924, 13 items. (Box-folder 29:1)
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1925-1932, 17 items. (Box-folder 29:2)
    Blanche wrote about the nightmare of the stock market crash and how badly it hurt them. They lost everything and she had to get a job as a nurse. She also mentioned how "dreadful about the Lindbergh baby."
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1932-1939, 15 items. (Box-folder 29:3)
  - Blanche S. Ross and Ross Family to Ada, 1940-1954; n. d., 19 items. (Box-folder 29:4)
  - Other Correspondence of Blanche Shriner Ross, 1881-1924, 9 items. (Box-folder 29:5)
  - Charles Broadway Rouss, 1901; n.d, 3 items. (Box-folder 29:6)
  - Rouss Family General Correspondence, 1894-1922, 42 items. (Box-folder 29:7)
  - Albert Romero, 1891-1894, 22 items. (Box-folder 29:8)
  - John Scott, 1903; 1914, 4 items. (Box-folder 30:1)
    John Scott, a friend or acquaintance of Ada's, wrote to her giving permission to use his name as a reference for Thomas Beardsworth and offering to write a letter to his friend Paul Bowles in support of Professor Beardsworth.
  - Ella Shields, 1895-1900, 16 items. (Box-folder 30:2)
    Ella Shields was a close friend of Ada's from Winchester who moved to Baltimore, Maryland and who wrote many letters to Ada and her mother.
  - Ella Shields, 1901-1951; n. d, 16 items. (Box-folder 30:3)
  - February George Shoenfelt, 1900-1902, 9 items. (Box-folder 30:4)
    George Shoenfelt was madly in love with Ada and tried to convince her to marry him instead of Thomas Beardsworth. Ada corresponded with him frequently and encouraged his affections. She was trying to engage his help to obtain a position for her in the post office.
  - George Shoenfelt, 1902 March, 15 items. (Box-folder 30:5)
  - George Shoenfelt, 1902 April, 16 items. (Box-folder 30:6)
  - George Shoenfelt, 1902 May, 9 items. (Box-folder 30:7)
  - George Shoenfelt, 1902 June, 15 items. (Box-folder 30:8)
  - George Shoenfelt, 1902 July-December, 11 items. (Box-folder 30:9)
  - George Shoenfelt, 1903-1905; n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 30:10)
  - Mame Shriner (Mary Johnston), 1883; 1890-1892, 14 items. (Box-folder 31:1)
    Mame Shriner wrote to Ada and her mother Muddie about skating, and about boys in her school. There are also letters from her friends Will [Glass] and Emma [sister of William "Billy" Powell].
  - Mame Shriner, 1893-1895, 12 items. (Box-folder 31:2)
    Mame mentioned the World Fair in Chicago and described her feelings of rebellion against her strict father and related that Ada was in the same situation with her father.
  - Mame Shriner, 1898-1902, 16 items. (Box-folder 31:3)
    In December of 1900 Mame took the Postal Civil Service Exam and in 1901 Mame explained to Ada the Civil Service procedures for accepting applicants and mentioned her personal interviews with Senator Louis E. McComas from Baltimore Maryland.
  - Mame Shriner, 1903-1905, 10 items. (Box-folder 31:4)
    Mame wrote about working as a stenographer for Senator Levi Ankeny from Washington State. She also invited Ada and Muddy to the presidential inauguration of Theodore Roosevelt.
  - Mame Shriner [Johnston], 1906-1931; n.d., 13 items. (Box-folder 31:5)
    1907 Mame was trying to help Ada find work possibly embroidering shirtwaists for the Senator's wife, Mrs. Levi Ankeny. In 1913 Mame married Arthur Johnston who did not have steady work, and borrowed money from Mame. In 1931 Mame described the serious financial troubles of her sister Blanche and the depression. She mentioned the closing of the Central Trust Company's Bank, G. Bryan Pitts of F. H. Smith Company and Emory Coblentz and their indictments of fraud.
  - Mame Shriner, n. d. (Box-folder 31:6)
  - UVa and Thomas Beardsworth, 1899-1930; n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 31:7)
    There are letters from the Secretary of the University of Virginia R. M. Price to Thomas Beardsworth, leader of the Stonewall Band Brigade (1906) requesting music for the opening of classes.
  - Armistead Webb, 1915-1920; n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 31:8)
    There are cards and notes from a friend and insurance broker Armistead Webb.
  - Dr. T. Clayton Williams, 1894-1903; n.d., 16 items. (Box-folder 31:9)
    Dr. Williams wrote to Ada as a close friend of her family and as the family doctor.
  - Woodrow Wilson Family General Correspondence and Other VIP's, 1884-1921, 24 items. (Box-folder 31:10)
    Correspondents include Madison Wilson, Gilmer Schley, Mrs. George Frances Wilson, Sidney A. Moss, Hattie Wilson, A. Conan Doyle, William [Gibbs] McAdoo (1863-1941), Gerneral Fitz-John Porter. There are also news clippings of Mrs. Wilson's funeral and a program with John Fitzgerald Kennedy's signature. Also included is Robert E. Byrd, Jr's signature.
- Series II: Topical
  - Businesses owned by women, 1891-1914, 11 items. (Box-folder 32:1)
  - Businesses owned by women, 1915-1921, 19 items. (Box-folder 32:2)
  - Businesses owned by women, 1922-1943; n.d., 18 items. (Box-folder 32:3)
  - Businesses owned by women- Adas's Application for Arts and Crafts Shop, 1915, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:4)
  - Church, 1887; 1900; n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 32:5)
    Programs.
  - Diary kept by Ada, 1895-1897; n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 32:6)
  - Dress design, n. d., 3 items. (Box-folder 32:7)
    Hand drawn design of a dress and papers doll cut outs.
  - Financial, 1860-1911, 33 items. (Box-folder 32:8)
  - Financial-Ada's will, 1910, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:9)
  - Financial, 1912-1919, 32 items. (Box-folder 32:10)
  - Financial, 1920-1923, 16 items. (Box-folder 32:11)
  - Financial, 1924-1928, 39 items. (Box-folder 32:12)
  - Financial, 1930-1939, 21 items. (Box-folder 32:13)
  - Financial, 1940-1949, 21 items. (Box-folder 32:14)
  - Financial, 1950-1956; n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 32:15)
  - Financial Diaries and Ledgers of Thomas Beardsworth Including Music Lesson Book, n. d., 6 items. (Box-folder 33:1)
  - Health- Medical, 1920; 1928; n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 33:2)
  - Miscellaneous- Lists, n. d., 4 items. (Box-folder 33:3)
  - Miscellaneous- Map of Europe, n. d., 11 items. (Box-folder 33:4)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, n. d., 2 items. (Box-folder 33:5)
  - Miscellaneous, n. d., 11 items. (Box-folder 33:6)
  - Miscellaneous, n. d., 5 items. (Box-folder 33:7)
    Includes Deland cabinet maker brochures.
  - Music, 1928, 1 item. (Box-folder 33:8)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1890-1899, 48 items. (Box-folder 33:9)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1900-1905, 47 items. (Box-folder 33:10)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1906-1907, 39 items. (Box-folder 33:11)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1908-1910, 13 items. (Box-folder 33:12)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1911-1913, 28 items. (Box-folder 33:13)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1914, 19 items. (Box-folder 33:14)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1915, 35 items. (Box-folder 33:15)
  - Photographs, n. d. (Box 34)
  - Photographs, n. d. (Box 35)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1916 January-August, 25 items. (Box-folder 36:1)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1916 September-December, 35 items. (Box-folder 36:2)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1917-1918, 35 items. (Box-folder 36:3)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1919-1920, 40 items. (Box-folder 36:4)
  - March Receipts and Orders, 1921-1922, 31 items. (Box-folder 36:5)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1922 April-1923, 30 items. (Box-folder 36:6)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1924, 21 items. (Box-folder 36:7)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1925, 29 items. (Box-folder 36:8)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1926-1927 March, 24 items. (Box-folder 36:9)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1927 April-1930, 28 items. (Box-folder 37:1)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1931-1936, 37 items. (Box-folder 37:2)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1937, 31 items. (Box-folder 37:3)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1938-1939, 15 items. (Box-folder 37:4)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1940-1949, 32 items. (Box-folder 37:5)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1950-1955, 12 items. (Box-folder 37:6)
  - Receipts and Orders, n. d., 3 items. (Box-folder 37:7)
  - Receipts and Orders, n. d., 53 items. (Box-folder 37:8)
  - Receipts and Orders, n.d., 84 items. (Box-folder 37:9)
  - Receipts and Orders, 1894-1935; n.d., 21 items. (Box-folder 37:10)
  - Recipes, n.d., 10 items. (Box-folder 37:11)
  - Ada-References, 1899, 3 items. (Box-folder 37:12)
    Handwritten letters of recommendation for Ada Bantz Beardsworth from friends.
  - Ada's Report Card-Episcopal Female Institute, 1882-1883, 4 items. (Box-folder 37:13)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Ada, 1912-1948; n.d., 12 items. (Box-folder 38:1)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Ada and Tom, n. d., 1 item. (Box-folder 38:2)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Correspondence and Invitations, 1896-1919, 26 items. (Box-folder 38:3)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Correspondence and Invitations, 1920-1933, 18 items. (Box-folder 38:4)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Correspondence and Invitations, 1935-1941, 6 items. (Box-folder 38:5)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Correspondence and Invitations, n. d., 19 items. (Box-folder 38:6)
  - Staunton Military Academy -Former Students and Parents, 1909-1914, 16 items. (Box-folder 38:7)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1915-1916, 26 items. (Box-folder 38:8)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Former Students and Parents, 1917, 26 items. (Box-folder 38:9)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Former Students and Parents, 1918-1919, 37 items. (Box-folder 38:10)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Former Students and Parents, 1920 January-September, 17 items. (Box-folder 38:11)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1920 October-December, 20 items. (Box-folder 39:1)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Former Students and Parents, 1921 January-September, 31 items. (Box-folder 39:2)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Former Students and Parents, 1921 October-1924 September, 21 items. (Box-folder 39:3)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1924 October-1926, 23 items. (Box-folder 39:4)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1927-1931, 19 items. (Box-folder 39:5)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1932, 17 items. (Box-folder 39:6)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1933-1936, 21 items. (Box-folder 39:7)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Former Students and Parents, 1937-1948; n. d., 31 items. (Box-folder 39:8)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Other Correspondence, 1911; 1929, 2 items. (Box-folder 39:9)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Dance Cardbooks, n. d., 15 items. (Box-folder 39:10)
  - Staunton Military Academy Lessons, 1917-1925; n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 40:1)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Lessons- Hannah A. Babcock, 1894, 2 items. (Box-folder 40:2)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Tom- List of Students, n. d., 2 items. (Box-folder 40:3)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Notebooks, n. d., 3 items. (Box-folder 40:4)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Procedures and Insignia, 1933; n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 40:5)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Tom-General Correspondence, Tuition, and Music, 1985; 1900-1919, 28 items. (Box-folder 40:6)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Tom- General Correspondence, Tuition, and Music, 1920-1921, 24 items. (Box-folder 40:7)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Tom- General Correspondence, Tuition, and Music, 1922-1923, 17 items. (Box-folder 40:8)
  - Staunton Military Academy-Tom-General Correspondence, Tuition, and Music, 1924-1925, 8 items. (Box-folder 40:9)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Tom- General Correspondence, Tuition, and Music, 1927-1934, 18 items. (Box-folder 40:10)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Tom- General Correspondence, Tuition, and Music, 1935-1938, 11 items. (Box-folder 40:11)
  - Staunton Military Academy- Concert Tickets, n. d., 15 items. (Box-folder 40:12)
  - Staunton Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, 1906-1919; n.d., 16 items. (Box-folder 40:13)
  - Virginia Female Institute- Stuart Hall, 1933; n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 40:14)
  - Travel, 1910-1919, 13 items. (Box-folder 41:1)
  - Travel, 1920-1925, 21 items. (Box-folder 41:2)
  - Travel, 1927-1943; n. d., 22 items. (Box-folder 41:3)
  - Writings by T. Marion Bantz, n. d., 5 items. (Box-folder 41:4)
  - Writings miscellaneous, 1890-1895; n.d., 52 items. (Box-folder 41:5)